Finding Aid for Topographic Quadrangle Maps, 1895-[ongoing].
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Topographic Quadrangle Maps 1895-[ongoing]
Geological Survey (U.S.)
2700 maps color; approximate
M 4110 svar G4 [2010130]
Topographic quadrangle maps for Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Principal donors, Library of Michigan (donor 156 2, ca. 900 maps), New York State Library (donor 7453, ca. 1,200 maps); smaller groups of maps from several other donors (ca. 600 maps).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open without restriction.
Beginning in 1895, the U. S. Geological Survey published several series of topographic maps of Michigan at different scales and covering different size quadrangles (quadrangles are areas bounded by parallels of latitude and meridians of longitude). By the 1980s, the entire state had been mapped in one or another series of topographic maps. These maps show a variety of geographic features, including cultural features such as roads, buildings, and cemeteries, hydrographic features such as lakes and rivers, topographic features shown by contour lines and elevations, and vegetation. Maps of some areas of the state, especially southeastern Michigan, have been revised and reissued at more-or-less regular intervals, allowing users to trace urban development, erosion, and other changes over time. Other areas of the state, especially the northern Lower Peninsula and eastern Upper Peninsula, have been mapped only once.
Although many series of topographic maps have been issued for Michigan, The Michigan Historical Collections has collected only the following:
15 Minute, Scale 1:62,500: This was the first series issued for Michigan, beginning in 1895. The last new maps in this series were issued in 1963. The scale is about one mile to an inch. Each map covers an area 15 minutes of latitude by 15 minutes of longitude (or about 17 by 13 miles in the southern part of the state). Early maps in this series do not show vegetation.
15 Minute, Scale 1:48,000: Maps in this series were issued in the 1910s and 1920s, apparently as advance editions for 1:62,500 maps. The scale is about 3/4 of a mile to an inch, and each map covers a 15 minute by 15 minute area. Maps in this series do not show vegetation.
7.5 Minute, Scale 1:24,000: First published in 1934, this series began to replace the 1:62,500 series as the standard size for topographic maps. From 1963 to about 1980 all larger scale topographic maps for Michigan were issued in this series. (Beginning about 1980 publication of a new 1:25,000 series began, but publication of the 1:24,000 series continued.) The scale is 2,000 feet to an inch, or about 1/3 of a mile to an inch. Each map covers an area 7.5 minutes of latitude by 7.5 minutes of longitude (or about 8.5 miles by 6.5 miles in the southern part of the state). These maps are produced both with and without a green overprint showing vegetation. The Michigan Historical Collections collection of this series includes some of each type.
7.5 Minute, Scale 1:25,000: Maps in this series were first published about 1980. The maps are very similar to those in the 1:24,000 series except for the slightly different scale based on the metric system. The scale is 1/4 kilometer per centimeter, or about .4 miles to an inch. At this time, the Michigan Historical Collections holds only a small portion of the maps published in this series.
7.5 Minute, Scale 1:31,680: This series was issued in the 1930s and 1940s, mainly identified as "advance sheets" or "preliminary editions." Some of these maps do not show topography, but other than that they are very similar to those in the 1:24,000 series. The scale is 1/2 mile to an inch.
Specials: A few topographic maps have been issued for areas other than the normal quadrangles. Those held by the Michigan Historical Collections are found in this series.
Index Maps: Index maps have been published at irregular intervals by the Geological Survey to show all topographic maps in print for Michigan at the time of their publication.
Folios: In the early period of publication of topographic maps, folios were published for various quadrangles which included topographic and geological maps as well as text describing the geology of the area. Three folios were published for Michigan quadrangles: Ann Arbor, Detroit, and Menominee. The Ann Arbor and Menominee folios are cataloged in the atlas collection (MH/4/W319/1908/R963 and MH/4/W319/1915/R963 for two editions of the Ann Arbor folio, MH/3/M5/U58/1900 for Menominee). The Detroit folio is cataloged in the book collection (EB/2/W359/S554) and the maps have been removed and cataloged in the map collection (M/4113/.W3/1916/S5).
Other series of topographic maps have been issued by the Geological Survey, including maps at scales of 1:50,000, 1:100,000, and 1:250,000. Maps in these series, as well as maps lacking from the series held by the Michigan Historical Collections, may be found in the Map Library, 8th Floor, Hatcher Graduate Library, on Central Campus.
Some topographic maps of Michigan have been published by the U. S. Army Map Service and the U. S. Forest Service. Maps in these series are cataloged separately.
U. S. Geological Survey topographic maps held by the Michigan Historical Collections are listed in this finding aid. For each of the series described above, the maps are listed alphabetically. The titles are listed as shown on the maps themselves and on the index maps. Topographic maps are named for a prominent town or physical feature located near the center of the quadrangle. Other information shown for each map includes:
Coordinate location for the map. For the 7.5 Minute series this consists of the Geological Survey code for the quadrangle, based on 1-degree blocks of latitude and longitude plus an alphanumeric for each map. For other series this consists of the latitude and longitude of the southeast corner of the map.
The latest survey date listed in the lower left hand corner of the map. This is almost always the same as the date shown on the index maps (major exceptions are photorevised maps, which are indexed under the date shown here as the reprint date, and maps published in the 1980s, which are indexed under the date shown here as the print date).
The printing or edition date shown prominently in the lower right hand corner of the map.
The reprint date; the actual date of printing of the map. Reprints of maps with the same print date sometimes contain revisions. In the case of photorevised maps, the reprint date shown here is the date of the photorevision.
Whether the map was printed with a green overprint showing vegetation.
Whether the map is photorevised, or revised from aerial photographs without field checks.
Using the index maps in conjunction with this finding aid will allow a researcher to determine whether topographic maps exist for a particular area and whether the Michigan Historical Collections holds those maps.
Subjects:
Michigan--Topographic maps.
Genre Terms:
Maps.
- 15 Minute, Scale 1:62,500
  - Alba-Evart
    - Alba N4445 W8445 (Folder Alba-Big Rapids)
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1958, green overprint
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1975, green overprint
    - Allegan N4230 W8545
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1959, green overprint
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1966, green overprint
    - Alma N4315 W8430
      - Survey 1935; print 1938, green overprint
      - Survey 1935; print 1935; reprint 1959, green overprint
      - Survey 1935; print 1935; reprint 1971, green overprint
    - Alvordton N4130 W8415
      - Survey 1911; print 1913, green overprint
      - Survey 1911; print 1913; reprint 1941
    - Atlanta N4500 W8400
      - Survey 1955; print 1955; reprint 1956, green overprint
      - Survey 1955; print 1955; reprint 1968, green overprint
    - Au Train N4615 W8645
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1959, green overprint
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1969, green overprint
    - Baldwin N4345 W8545
      - Survey 1959; print 1959; reprint 1960, green overprint
      - Survey 1959; print 1959; reprint 1971, green overprint
    - Bangor N4215 W8600
      - Survey 1927; print 1931
      - Survey 1927; print 1927; reprint 1959, green overprint
    - Bar Lake N4415 W8615
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1958, green overprint
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1968, green overprint
    - Bark River N4530 W8715
      - Survey 1963; print 1963; reprint 1964, green overprint
    - Battle Creek N4215 W8500
      - Survey 1917; print 1918, green overprint
      - Survey 1917; print 1932; reprint 1942
      - Survey 1947; print 1950, green overprint
    - Bay City N4330 W8345
      - Survey 1916; print 1919, green overprint
      - Survey 1916; print 1919; reprint 1943
    - Bayshore N4515 W8500
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1959, green overprint
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1973, green overprint
    - Beaver Island N4530 W8530
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1959, green overprint
    - Beechwood N4600 W8845
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1957, green overprint
    - Benton Harbor N4200 W8615
      - Survey 1927; print 1930, green overprint
        [in oversize folder]
      - Survey 1927; print 1930; reprint 1946
      - Survey 1927; print 1927; reprint 1964, green overprint
    - Bergland N4630 W8W930
      - Survey 1956; print 1956, green overprint
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1966, green overprint
    - Big Bay N4645 W8730
      - Survey 1954; print 1954; reprint 1956, green overprint
      - Survey 1954; print 1954; reprint 1965, green overprint
    - Big Rapids N4330 W8515
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1960, green overprint
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1965, green overprint
    - Blissfield N4145 W8345 (Folder Blissfield-Comins)
      - Survey 1939; print 1941
      - Survey 1939; print 1941, green overprint
      - Survey 1939; print 1939; reprint 1958, green overprint
    - Boulder Junction N4600 W8W930
      - Survey 1955; print 1955; reprint 1964, green overprint
      - Survey 1955; print 1955; reprint 1972, green overprint
    - Boyne City N4500 W8500
      - Survey 1961; print 1961; reprint 1963, green overprint
      - Survey 1961; print 1961; reprint 1971, green overprint
    - Boyne Falls N4500 W8445
      - Survey 1961; print 1961; reprint 1963, green overprint
      - Survey 1961; print 1961; reprint 1973, green overprint
    - Brimley N4615 W8430
      - Survey 1951; print 1951; reprint 1958, green overprint
    - Burt N4300 W8345
      - Survey 1919; print 1921, green overprint
      - Survey 1919; print 1919; reprint 1959
    - Cadillac North N4415 W8515
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1958, green overprint
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1971, green overprint
    - Cadillac South N4400 W8515
      - Survey 1957; print 1957; reprint 1959, green overprint
      - Survey 1957; print 1957; reprint 1976, green overprint
    - Carp River N4645 W8W945
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1957, green overprint
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1961, green overprint
    - Cassopolis N4145 W8600
      - Survey 1945; print 1947, green overprint
      - Survey 1945; print 1945; reprint 1967, green overprint
    - Cedar River N4515 W8715
      - Survey 1963; print 1963; reprint 1964, green overprint
    - Cedar Springs N4300 W8530
      - Survey 1916; print 1918, green overprint
      - Survey 1916; print 1918; reprint 1951
    - Central Lake N4500 W8515
      - Survey 1954; print 1954; reprint 1955, green overprint
      - Survey 1954; print 1954; reprint 1967, green overprint
    - Chambers Island N4500 W8715
      - Survey 1961; print 1961; reprint 1963, green overprint
      - Survey 1961; print 1961; reprint 1972, green overprint
    - Champion N4630 W8745
      - Survey 1955; print 1955; reprint 1957, green overprint
      - Survey 1955; print 1955; reprint 1963, green overprint
    - Charlevoix N4515 W8515
      - Survey 1954; print 1954; reprint 1955, green overprint
      - Survey 1954; print 1954; reprint 1969, green overprint
    - Charlotte N4230 W8445
      - Survey 1946; print 1949, green overprint
    - Cheboygan N4530 W8415
      - Survey 1957; print 1957; reprint 1958, green overprint
      - Survey 1957; print 1957; reprint 1971, green overprint
    - Chesaning N4300 W8400
      - Survey 1915; print 1917, green overprint
      - Survey 1915; print 1917; reprint 1941, green overprint
    - Clare N4345 W8445
      - Survey 1959; print 1959; reprint 1960, green overprint
    - Comins N4445 W8400
      - Survey 1955; print 1955; reprint 1956, green overprint
      - Survey 1955; print 1955; reprint 1970, green overprint
    - Cooks N4545 W8615 (Folder Cooks-Evart)
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1959, green overprint
    - Copemish N4415 W8545
      - Survey 1957; print 1957; reprint 1958, green overprint
      - Survey 1957; print 1957; reprint 1967, green overprint
    - Corner Lake N4600 W8630
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1959, green overprint
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1968, green overprint
    - Corunna N4245 W8400
      - Survey 1926; print 1929, green overprint
      - Survey 1926; print 1958, green overprint
      - Survey 1926; print 1926; reprint 1971, green overprint
    - Cross Village N4530 W8500
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1959, green overprint
    - Crystal Falls N4600 W8815
      - Survey 1895; print 1899
      - Survey 1895; print 1899; reprint 1910
    - Custer N4345 W8600
      - Survey 1959; print 1959; reprint 1960, green overprint
    - De Witt N4245 W8430
      - Survey 1925; print 1927
      - Survey 1925; print 1927; reprint 1950
    - Detroit N4215 W8300
      - Survey 1904; print 1905
      - Survey 1904; print 1905; reprint 1915
        [also in Detroit folio]
    - Dexter N4215 W8345
      - Survey 1902; print 1906
      - Survey 1902; print 1906; reprint 1941
      - Survey 1902; print 1902; reprint 1962
    - Dundee N4145 W8330
      - Survey 1939; print 1941
      - Survey 1939; print 1939; reprint 1968, green overprint
    - Durand N4245 W8345
      - Survey 1920; print 1922, green overprint
      - Survey 1920; print 1922; reprint 1950
    - East Tawas N4415 W8315
      - Survey 1959; print 1959; reprint 1960, green overprint
      - Survey 1959; print 1959; reprint 1972, green overprint
    - Eckerman N4615 W8500
      - Survey 1951; print 1951; reprint 1958, green overprint
    - Elk Rapids N4445 W8515
      - Survey 1957; print 1957; reprint 1958, green overprint
    - Ellison Bay N4515 W8700
      - Survey 1960; print 1960; reprint 1971, green overprint
    - Elsie N4300 W8415
      - Survey 1916; print 1918, green overprint
      - Survey 1916; print 1918; reprint 1950
    - Empire N4445 W8600
      - Survey 1957; print 1957; reprint 1958, green overprint
      - Survey 1957; print 1957; reprint 1969, green overprint
    - Escanaba N4530 W8700
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1959, green overprint
    - Evart N4345 W8515
      - Survey 1959; print 1959; reprint 1960, green overprint
      - Survey 1959; print 1959; reprint 1972, green overprint
  - Fairport-Manistee
    - Fairport N4530 W8630 (Folder Fairport-Gobles)
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1959, green overprint
    - Fennville N4230 W8600
      - Survey 1928; print 1931
      - Survey 1928; print 1931; reprint 1939
      - Survey 1928; print 1928; reprint 1965, green overprint
    - Fife Lake N4430 W8515
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1958, green overprint
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1965, green overprint
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1974, green overprint
    - Fletcher N4430 W8445
      - Survey 1949; print 1949; reprint 1955, green overprint
    - Flint N4300 W8330
      - Survey 1920; print 1920, green overprint
      - Survey 1920; print 1922, green overprint
      - Survey 1920; print 1920; reprint 1952, green overprint
      - Survey 1920; print 1920; reprint 1965, green overprint
    - Foster City N4545 W8730
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1957, green overprint
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1966, green overprint
    - Fowlerville N4230 W8400
      - Survey 1908; print 1910
      - Survey 1908; print 1908; reprint 1969
    - Frankfort N4430 W8600
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1958, green overprint
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1966, green overprint
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1975, green overprint
    - Freesoil N4400 W8600
      - Survey 1957; print 1957; reprint 1958, green overprint
      - Survey 1957; print 1957; reprint 1975, green overprint
    - Fremont N4315 W8545
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1960, green overprint
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1969, green overprint
    - Galesburg N4215 W8515
      - Survey 1917; print 1918, green overprint
      - Survey 1917; print 1930; reprint 1942
      - Survey 1947; print 1950, green overprint
      - Survey 1947; print 1947; reprint 1965, green overprint
    - Garden N4545 W8630
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1959, green overprint
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1968, green overprint
    - Gaylord N4500 W8430
      - Survey 1954; print 1954; reprint 1954, green overprint
    - Gladstone N4545 W8700
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1959, green overprint
    - Glennie N4430 W8330
      - Survey 1959; print 1959; reprint 1961, green overprint
      - Survey 1959; print 1959; reprint 1967, green overprint
    - Gobles N4215 W8545
      - Survey 1946; print 1948
      - Survey 1948; print 1949
      - Survey 1948; print 1948; reprint 1964, green overprint
    - Grace N4530 W8400 (Folder Grace-Hog Island)
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1959, green overprint
    - Grand Portal Point N4630 W8615
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1959, green overprint
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1974, green overprint
    - Grand Rapids N4245 W8530
      - Survey 1912; print 1914, green overprint
      - Survey 1912; print 1914; reprint 1943
      - Survey 1912; print 1914; reprint 1950
    - Grandville N4245 W8545
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1959, green overprint
    - Grayling N4430 W8430
      - Survey 1949; print 1949; reprint 1955, green overprint
    - Greenland N4645 W8W900
      - Survey 1950; print 1951, green overprint
      - Survey 1950; print 1950; reprint 1966, green overprint
    - Grosse Pointe N4215 W8245
      - Survey 1904; print 1905; reprint 1915
      - Survey 1904; print 1905
    - Gull Island N4530 W8545
      - Survey 1955; print 1955; reprint 1959, green overprint
    - Gwinn N4615 W8715
      - Survey 1952; print 1952; reprint 1954, green overprint
      - Survey 1952; print 1952; reprint 1975, green overprint
    - Harrison N4400 W8445
      - Survey 1957; print 1957; reprint 1958, green overprint
      - Survey 1957; print 1957; reprint 1973, green overprint
    - Harrisville N4430 W8315
      - Survey 1959; print 1959; reprint 1961, green overprint
      - Survey 1959; print 1959; reprint 1973, green overprint
    - Hart N4330 W8615
      - Survey 1959; print 1959; reprint 1961, green overprint
      - Survey 1959; print 1959; reprint 1968, green overprint
    - Hartford N4200 W8600
      - Survey 1927; print 1931, green overprint
      - Survey 1927; print 1927; reprint 1967, green overprint
    - Hastings N4230 W8515
      - Survey 1951; print 1951; reprint 1953, green overprint
      - Survey 1951; print 1951; reprint 1973, green overprint
    - Herman N4630 W8815
      - Survey 1955; print 1955; reprint 1956, green overprint
      - Survey 1955; print 1955; reprint 1965, green overprint
      - Survey 1955; print 1955; reprint 1976, green overprint
    - Hesperia N4330 W8600
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1959, green overprint
      - Survey 1958; print 1958; reprint 1969, green overprint
    - Hetherton N4500 W8415
      - Survey 1954; print 1954; reprint 1956, green overprint
      - Survey 1954; print 1954; reprint 1972, green overprint
    - Hillman N4500 W8345
      - Survey 1955; print 1955; reprint 1956, green overprint
      - Survey 1955; print 1955; reprint 1972, green overprint
    - Hog Island N4545 W8515
      - Survey 1955; print 1955; reprint 1958, green overprint
    - Holland N4245 W8600 (Folder Holland-Kenton)
      - Survey 1929; print 1932, green overprint
      - Survey 1929; print 1929; reprint 1965
    - Holly N4245 W8330
      - Survey 1920; print 1922, green overprint
      - Survey 1920; print 1920; reprint 1964
    - Homer N4200 W8445
      - Survey 1948; print 1949, green overprint
      - Survey 1948; print 1948; reprint 1968, green overprint
      - Survey 1948; print 1948; reprint 1977, green overprint
    - Houghton N4700 W8830
      - Survey 1912; print 1915, green overprint
      - Survey 1912; print 1915; reprint 1947
      - Survey 1952; print 1954; reprint 1959, green overprint
      - Survey 1952; print 1954; reprint 1964, green overprint
    - Houghton Lake N4415 W8445
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1958, green overprint
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1966, green overprint
    - Howard City N4315 W8515
      - Survey 1959; print 1959; reprint 1960, green overprint
    - Howell N4230 W8345
      - Survey 1907; print 1909
      - Survey 1907; print 1909; reprint 1932
      - Survey 1907; print 1909; reprint 1965
    - Huron Mountain N4645 W8745
      - Survey 1954; print 1954; reprint 1956, green overprint
      - Survey 1954; print 1954; reprint 1965, green overprint
    - Ionia N4245 W8500
      - Survey 1916; print 1918, green overprint
      - Survey 1916; print 1916; reprint 1972, green overprint
    - Iron River N4600 W8830
      - Survey 1895; print 1898
      - Survey 1895; print 1898; reprint 1910
    - Ironwood N4615 W9000
      - Survey 1955; print 1955; reprint 1957, green overprint
      - Survey 1955; print 1955; reprint 1961, green overprint
    - Ishpeming N4615 W8730
      - Survey 1952; print 1952; reprint 1954, green overprint
      - Survey 1952; print 1952; reprint 1969, green overprint
    - Jackson N4200 W8415
      - Survey 1935; print 1939
      - Survey 1935; print 1939; reprint 1950
      - Survey 1935; print 1935; reprint 1955
      - Survey 1935; print 1935; reprint 1968, green overprint
    - Kalamazoo N4215 W8530
      - Survey 1916; print 1918, green overprint
      - Survey 1916; print 1918; reprint 1946
      - Survey 1916; print 1916; reprint 1963, green overprint
    - Kalkaska N4430 W8500
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1957, green overprint
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1973, green overprint
    - Kenton N4615 W8845
      - Survey 1954; print 1954; reprint 1956, green overprint
      - Survey 1954; print 1954; reprint 1966, green overprint
    - Keweenaw Bay N4645 W8815 (Folder Keweenaw Bay-Manistee)
      - Survey 1954; print 1954; reprint 1956, green overprint
      - Survey 1954; print 1954; reprint 1958, green overprint
    - Kingsley N4430 W8530
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1958, green overprint
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1965, green overprint
    - Laingsburg N4245 W8415
      - Survey 1926; print 1928
      - Survey 1926; print 1928; reprint 1950
    - Lake N4345 W8500
      - Survey 1959; print 1959; reprint 1960, green overprint
      - Survey 1959; print 1959; reprint 1973, green overprint
    - Lake City N4415 W8500
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1958, green overprint
      - Survey 1956; print 1956; reprint 1968, green overprint
    - Lake George N4615 W8400
      - Survey 1951; print 1951; reprint 1958, green overprint
    - Lake Harbor N4300 W8615
      - Survey 1930; print 1936
      - Survey 1930; print 1936; reprint 1950
    - Lansing N4230 W8430